A Guide to the Fulcher Family Papers, 1836-1889
Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College
Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College
Fulcher Family Papers 1836-1889
Special Collections, Kegley Library
2010.2
6 folders.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Mary B. Kegley in 2010.
Biographical Information
James Fulcher (14 April 1810-18 February 1882) was a blacksmith and farmer in Abingdon, Washington County, Virginia. He probably was a relative of Thomas Fulcher (1797-1829) and Sarah Fulcher of Wythe County, Virginia, judging from a chancery court case in Series II. James married Sarah Jones on 24 June 1830 in Washington County. According to census records (1850-1870) and marriage records, the children of James and Sarah included:
Nancy Martin Dickerson Fulcher, born ca. 1835 and married Leander Jackson Keller 2 August 1859. She died ca. 1867 and was buried in Sinking Spring Cemetery, Abingdon, Virginia.
Samuel Fulcher, born ca. 1838, served in Co. D, 1st Virginia Cavalry Regiment and died in 1862.
Eliza Fulcher, born ca. 1840-1841, married Francis M. Medley on 6 November 1866.
James Fulcher, born 1844, served in Co. D, 1st Virginia Cavalry Regiment and was elected lieutenant in April 1862. He was living in Knoxville, Tennessee ca. 1908.
George Hopkins Fulcher was born in 1848.
William O. Fulcher was born 1850.
Virginia Fulcher was born 1853 and married Fayett M. Bryant on 22 September 1870.
According to WPA Papers, James Fulcher worked as a blacksmith in Abingdon and was an "honest and industrious man." Unfortunately he suffered financial ruin and filed for bankruptcy probably during the 1850s. On the 1850 census he listed a worth of $2,000. By 1860 he had changed professions and recouped his losses; the 1860 census lists him as a farmer worth $10,000 in real estate and $2,300 in personal property.
Sarah (Sally) Jones Fulcher died between 1860 and 1867, a January 1860 letter from her son Samuel mentions her illness. James remarried on 26 September 1867 to Nancy Red and continued farming in Abingdon. James and Nancy had two daughters, Molly A. Fulcher and Margaret R. Fulcher.
Fulcher continued farming in his later years. According to the 1870 census he possessed $3,000 in real estate and $800 in personal property. According to WPA Papers, James Fulcher died on 18 February 1882 and is buried in the Sinking Springs Cemetery in Abingdon, Virginia. Nancy Reid Fulcher died 14 January 1903 and is buried in Sinking Springs.
Scope and Content
The Fulcher Family Papers chronicle the life of James Fulcher and his extended family and consists of four series including Correspondence, Financial Records, Land and Legal Records, and Miscellaneous Records.
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence. 1840-1874, undated., 3 folders.
  - Folder 1. Correspondence. 1840, 1848-1849.
    - Folder 1. Correspondence. 1840, 1848-1849., 2 p.; torn. (Folder-item 1:1)
      Re: desires Fulcher to bring Jim and Sindy back and our children. He writes that William Y. C. White proposed letting him have Jim and Sindy and if White is willing to entrust you with the negroes bring them if not, hire Bill Dutton and his wife to come with you.
    - Letter. [unknown] to James Fulcher, Abingdon, Virginia. 5 January 1846., 1 p. (Folder-item 1:2)
      Re: requests that he ask Abel Pennington, confined in jail, if he would agree to sell his horse and wagon in order to pay debt. Peter Henritze has the horse and wagon which will now bring more than $40 but if they are kept until court they will not bring that much.
    - Letter. Christopher C. Stailey, Rural Retreat, Virginia to James Fulcher, Abingdon, Virginia. 13 August 1848., 3 p. (Folder-item 1:3)
      Re: disposition of slave Granville, who is owned by the Widow Fulcher [probably Sarah Fulcher, wife of Thomas Fulcher of Wythe who died 1829]. The Widow Fulcher wishes me to say to you that if you are willing to pay her for the time you have had Granville, she will keep him at home. Evidently Granville left James Fulcher's residence without permission to travel back to Wythe County. Granville stayed at Eli Davis' house.
    - Letter. Christian C. Stailey, Rural Retreat, Virginia to James Fulcher, Abingdon, Virginia. 17 September 1848., 2 p. (Folder-item 1:4)
      Re: Sarah Fulcher will live at George Killinger's house and her estate sale will include two slaves, Granville and Wesly. Staily inquires if Fulcher wants to buy them. [Sarah Fulcher, widow of Thomas who died in 1829 at age 32, is living with Christian C. Stailey in the 1860 census].
    - Letter. Thompson Thayer to [James Fulcher]. 22 October 1849., 1 p. (Folder-item 1:5)
      Re: request to let Andy Kingsolver have too dollars and charge the same to me in leather.
  - Folder 2. Correspondence. 1850-1859.
    - letter. J. M. Hill, Colesville, Stokes County, North Carolina to James Fulcher, Abingdon, Virginia. 30 October 1850., 2 p. (Folder-item 2:1)
      Re: notice that on application to Hunter for salt he said your contract to him was at 25 cents per bushel which is not agreeable to our contract.
    - Letter. Joseph Newland, Arcadia [Acadia], Virginia to Emanuel Bowser, Abingdon, Virginia. 4 November 1850., 1 p.; torn. (Folder-item 2:2)
      Re: request that Bowser come get his horse and settle his debt and recommends Charles B. Smith of Scott Court House, Scott County, as a renter for the horse.
    - Letter. Berry Johnson to [James] Fulcher. 13 June 1853., 1 p. (Folder-item 2:3)
      Re: request that Fulcher meet him at the store to settle payment for land.
    - Letter. James Fulcher to B. F. Buchanan. 21 November 1853., 1 p. (Folder-item 2:4)
      Re: request for twenty bushel of salt by J. Adams.
    - Letter. R. T. Wilkerson, Thorn Grove, Tennessee to James Fulcher. 4 June 1857., 2 p. (Folder-item 2:5)
      Re: debt he owes [unknown] Hilliard whom he thought was one of my best friends.
    - Letter. James A. Bailey, Montgomery Springs, Virginia to [James Fulcher]. 23 July 1857., 1 p. (Folder-item 2:6)
      Re: desire to lease land from the Bowen heirs to plant wheat.
  - Folder 3. Correspondence. 1860-1874, undated.
    - Letter. Samuel Fulcher, Fort Worth, Texas to James Fulcher, Abingdon, Virginia. 31 January 1860., 3 p. (Folder-item 3:1)
      Re: illness of his mother Sarah Jones Fulcher, journey to Texas on Mississippi River. We had a good time coming up the river shooting at alligators, ducks, geese and cranes. We saw alligators as large as John Anderson. He also writes about sinking of boat; rumor that Colonel Gillespie will return to Tazewell; John Cummings and the Graham boys; and abstinence from whiskey.
    - Letter. Charles W. Alderson to James Fulcher. 6 January 1871., 1 p. (Folder-item 3:2)
      Re: wheat and oats for William Terry.
    - Letter. Friend L. Garret, Stockton, Missouri to James Fulcher. 21 June 1874., 4 p. (Folder-item 3:3)
      Re: his farm of 200 acres; his wife and 3 children; price of wheat, corn, beef, bacon, etc. Unkle, this is the best farm country for raising stock you ever saw. A man can live at his ease. He also writes about visit of Samuel Jones and Aunt Mary and requests information on cousin Samuel Fulcher.
    - Letter. Friend L. Garret, Stockton, Missouri to James Fulcher. 6 September 1874., 3 p. (Folder-item 3:4)
      Re: ruin of his crops by Chinch bugs and drought and Fulcher's collection for sale of his land. I am sorry to hear of so mutch bad luck in your famley.
    - Letter. C. L. Davidson to [unknown] Neff. 8 September 1886., 1 p. (Folder-item 3:5)
      Re: request for him to see Mandy and get potatoes, beans, and corn.
- Series II. Financial Records. 1836-1880, 1 folder; 9 items.
  This series contains promissory notes from Logan Wallis, Greenway & Company, and James to Wooton and Robert Keys and a 1847 fine to William T. Fulcher for non-attendance at militia muster. Also included are receipts of James Fulcher and a 1873 Town of Abingdon tax ticket to James Fulcher (land valued at $3,489 and personal property $5.25).
- Series III. Land and Legal Records. 1837-1889, 1 folder.
  - Folder 1. Land and Legal Records. 1837-1889.
    - Chancery case, Washington County. 16 May 1837., 2 p. (Folder-item 1:1)
      William Clark, Polly Clark, Peter Rush, Susannah Rush vs. Benjamin Fulcher, James Fulcher, William Fulcher, John Fulcher, Rufus Fulcher, Ferdinand Fulcher; [Sarah] Fulcher, widow of Thomas Fulcher; William Fulcher, Emeline Fulcher, Sarah Jane Fulcher, the children and heirs of said Thomas Fulcher; Peter Killinger, Pleasant Smith, and Jacob Clark. Case concerned settlement of estate of Thomas Fulcher and debts paid to William Clark et al.
    - Warrant. 15 March 1844., 2 p. (Folder-item 1:2)
      Warrant for settlement of debt owed James Fulcher by George Graves, Washington County, Virginia, signed by Jno. D. Mitchell, Justice of the Peace. Mitchell orders the debt of $48.40 be settled from the estate of George Graves.
    - Circuit and Chancery Court Order. 30 April 1847., 2 p. (Folder-item 1:3)
      Court order, Fluvanna County, Virginia. William P. Dickinson, Asa D. Dickinson and heirs vs. William M. Dickinson and Pleasant Howard, executors of Thomas Dickinson, deceased, and others. Settlement regarding estate of Thomas Dickinson. On reverse: Abraham Shepherd, Fluvanna County, Virginia to J. B. Floyd, Abingdon Virginia providing him copy of order. 8 May 1847. The balance reported by Commissioner as due Nancy Fulcher on September 1842 is $272.76.
    - Agreement, Jacob Martin and George McCray. 24 April 1852., 2 p. (Folder-item 1:4)
      Agreement between Jacob Martin of Washington County, Virginia, and George McCray of Alamance County, North Carolina. Martin agrees to settle debt to McCray by selling him goods, wares, and mechanize in his store at cost. Witnessed by James Fulcher and Jacob Clark.
    - Appointment, Surveyor of Road. 6 July 1857., 2 p. (Folder-item 1:5)
      Notice from John G. Creger to sheriff of Washington County re: appointment of James Fulcher as surveyor of the public road leading from the fork at the foot of Greenways hill to the two mile tree. Tithable list for road maintenance includes James A. Clark, Joseph Haskew, Joel Adams, William Bryant, Francis Garrett, James Fulcher, John Wartz, and William Grubb.
    - Survey for Campbell St. John. 18 September 1857., 1 p. (Folder-item 1:6)
      Survey for Campbell St. John, 85 acres and 124 poles lying on the middle fork of the Holston River in Washington County, Virginia. Surveyed by J. A. McQuowen.
    - Summons for Gabriel Stickley, William King Heiskell, and James Fulcher. 8 October 1857., 1 p. (Folder-item 1:7)
      Summons for Gabriel Stickley, William King Heiskell, and James Fulcher to answer plea of Exchange Bank for debt of 4162.60.
    - Summons to James Fulcher. 26 October 1857., 1 p. (Folder-item 1:8)
      Summons to James Fulcher, trustee of George W. Anderson to answer bill against him in chancery court by Berry St. John.
    - Agreement between Sallie C. Thurston and John M. Newman. 1 February 1889., 1 p. (Folder-item 1:9)
      Agreement between Sallie C. Thurston and John M. Newman to lease land. Newman was to build a good log house, build fence, and plant three crops and not to use timber off land.
- Series IV. Miscellaneous Records. Undated., 1 item; 1 folder; 4 p.
  Undated eulogy for father written by unknown author. Mentions death of father as being 25 years ago, death of mother 2 years ago, and death of brother and 2 sisters; discusses financial ruin caused by his mother's lack of decision of character.